What happens when you want to look at a dynamic value?
In other words, when you can't predict the route that you're going to.
So take for instance, when we go into Pokédex,
and Pokédex has different Pokemon,
that is the way the Pokédex works.
What if we wanted to actually render out the different Pokemon,
but we wanted to do things based on the parameter in the URL?
So an example of this might be,
if we're looking at the Pokédex page and you say,
okay, theoretically what I'd like to be able to do is also then
go to a page that goes to like,
go to slash Pokédex slash one,
and that should call the first Pokemon.
In other words, this part is dynamic because what we don't want to do is define
one dot view, two dot view, and etc.
So how might that actually work?
Well, when it comes to that,
what we're actually looking at is around the idea of dynamic param IDs.
So the way this works is we go inside of our router,
inside of Playground.
What we have here is we have a path here,
that's slash Pokédex slash with the colon ID,
and this is what tells it that it's going to be dynamic.
Then from here, we can then say,
let's create a Pokemon page because this would fetch
a specific Pokemon in this particular case.
Let me FSC this and then let's just say Pokemon.
For now, we'll just say number 100 to show that it's
wrong as far as the URL is concerned.
Then we'll just do component and this time we'll just
import the path at views slash Pokemon page dot view. Save.
So to prove that this works,
we're going to go ahead and on the Pokédex page right here,
we will have a router link that goes to slash
Pokédex and this time we'll do slash 20,
just to show something different.
Go to Pokemon number 20.
We see that here, and if we click on this,
you'll see that it does correctly jump us over to the page.
But what we need is we need to be able to
pull in the dynamic data.
Right? How does that work?
Well, when you used to do it in View2,
the way you would do it in Options API and you could still
could is you do this dot route dot
params that's usually what you would reach out for.
But in an effort to get you all practicing with
composition API and seeing what
an alternative form might look like,
what might you reach for?
Probably a helper method, right?
So we have something called useRoute because it's from ViewRouter.
Then we can say constRoute equals useRoute.
Then before we do anything,
let's just log that out real quick and show you what we get.
Oh, this is the Pokédex page, I need to go back.
So on the Pokédex page,
you'll see now that we expand this out to the target,
it has a bunch of stuff actually,
params, name, meta,
and then if you broke it down to query stuff,
there's a whole ton of stuff
under there that you can unpack.
But the one we care about is going to be the parameters.
So let me go ahead and actually move this useRoute because
where we need it is not the Pokédex page,
we need it on the Pokemon page.
Let me drop this over here instead.
So now let's go ahead and go to Pokemon 20,
and now we'll notice actually we refresh.
There we go. We have our route being rendered,
and we look at our params,
you'll see that we have an ID of 20 in here.
Where does this ID come from?
This ID comes from what we named right here inside of our path.
That's where it's actually being defined.
So what we get if we want,
we say route.params.id,
and we do that and refresh the page,
you'll see there it is, 20.
That's all it takes.
So now your imagination can go from here,
you go to the Pokemon API,
and then when you load the page,
you can go ahead and fetch the right Pokemon,
get its attributes, render it to the page,
but for the sake of conciseness,
we're just going to go ahead and show that here,
just like this, route.params.id,
and then just like that,
you now have a dynamic page that can take any argument,
and then however you see fit,
you can programmatically set up else conditions,
if else whatever, not to render the right stuff to your users.
What about params for parent routes?
Okay, so the question here is around params for parent routes.
So what you're saying is that if it's like with,
so basically let's sketch this out real quick,
are you saying something like,
if Pokedex had then like on top of ID for the Pokemon,
there was like an additional thing for like element.
So then you might be on like an element page,
and you want to look at your ID params.
Potentially.
Yeah, so I believe the moment you do the route basically,
you should basically get everything
that comes as a part of that route.
And so this goes beyond the scope
of like the fundamentals review router,
but there's even things like nested views
and all those things that we can play around with.
So you should be able to get the parent
from that path without any problem.
And that's why it would be a good practice, for example,
not in your router.js to say,
to define another route that uses the same parameter like name.
Like you wouldn't want to be like ID ID.
Cause I think that would actually probably,
I'm almost certain that would break view router,
cause it would be confused.
And so in that particular case,
that's where it's important to be just specific
about what that parameter name is,
and then the route should contain all of those parameters
correctly appended into that object.
So you said nested routes, could you have like region
was the thing you were saying?
Yeah.
Region slash region ID, a region name.
Yep.
Underneath that have the pokedex for that region
and then have a poked Pokemon page.
Yeah.
The ID parameter on that.
We can.
And so it's not part of this exercise,
but since this is a question,
I do want to show this for the nested.
If we look at the docs right here,
and we look at nested routes,
the thing about nested routes is it's easy to think of it
like what we just did,
cause you see here a user Johnny profile, right?
You're like, didn't we just do this pokedex slash Pokemon?
This is different because a nested view means
that you have a router view inside of a router view,
meaning the rest of the page stays the same
and just that one section of the page changes
based on the URL.
So as you can see here inside of this example,
let me blow it up a lot,
is that the user page out here,
which is the shell, which is slash user,
is currently bringing in the Johnny child, right?
So it'd be user Johnny.
But the nested view here is for the profile and the posts.
And so you can almost think of it like tabs
where you don't want the whole page to re-render
if you click on post for Johnny.
You want everything else to stay the same,
you just want to switch the tab that's inside of it.
And so nested views are basically this concept
that without having to re-render the entire page,
you can just render a portion of it
and have that update based on the URL.
And so that can be highly performant as well
when it comes to doing things for your app.
So I know it's funny that nested views have had a resurgence
lately in the discussion,
but this has been in view for quite a while.
But I do want to make you all aware of it,
so that if you ever find that you're like,
oh, everything else needs to change,
or sorry, everything needs to stay the same,
except for this one part when the URL swaps,
nested views are nested routes, check this out,
this will solve your problems.